<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tools | The Analytic Bastard]]></title>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/categories/tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-13T22:17:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Analytic Bastard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Powering Up Python as a Data Analysis Platform]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/02/26/powering-up-python-as-a-data-analysis-platform/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T00:01:36+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/02/26/powering-up-python-as-a-data-analysis-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When working with Machine Learning algorithms we face large data movement, but in many algorithms the most important part is a heavy use of linear algebra operations and other mathematical/vectorial computations.</p>

<p>Intel has a math library that is optimized for the latest processors (MKL), including programmer-made optimizations for multiple core counts, wider vector units and more varied architectures which yield a performance that could not be achieved only with compiler automated optimization for routines such as highly vectorized and threaded linear algebra, fast Fourier transforms, and vector math and Statistics. These functions are royalty-free, so including them statically in the program comes at no cost.</p>

<p>Cristoph Gohlke and collaborators have a MKL license and have taken the effort to compile a series of Python modules compiled agaist them. In particular, Numpy and Scipy include these powerful libraries. Add to this that he has already compiled the binaries for Windows 64 bits which are very rare on the internet.</p>

<p>The following are two tests with a positive definite matrix. We compute the eigenvalues in R and Python, using the symmetric eigenvalue solver in each case. The processor is a i5 3210M not plugged in to the socket (losing approx. half its performance). Note that this version of R is compiled against standard Atlas libraries.</p>

<p><code>r
B=read.csv("B.csv",header=F)
st=proc.time(); eigB=eigen(B,symmetric=T); en=proc.time()
&gt; en-st
   user  system elapsed
   0.58    0.00    0.58 
</code></p>

<p>In Python:</p>

<p><code>python
from time import time
import numpy
B=numpy.loadtxt("B.csv", delimiter=",")
st = time(); U, E = numpy.linalg.eigh(B); en = time()
&gt;&gt;&gt; en-st
0.13400006294250488
</code></p>

<p>A final remark is that there exists an opensource alternative to high-performance CPU computing, and it is the OpenBLAS libraries. Their performance is comparable to MKL.</p>

<p>Link to the positive definite matrix used in the experiments <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/uxijs3jckckafra/B.7z">here</a>.
Link to Christoph Gohlke’s page <a href="http://www.lfd.uci.edu/~gohlke/pythonlibs/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Despite the fact that I’ve been aware of Scikits Learn (sklearn) for some time during my postgraduate years, I never got the chance to really use Python for data analysis and, instead, I had been a victim of my own inertia and limited myself to use R and especially Matlab.</p>

<p>I must say, in the beginning, Python looks awkward: it was inconceivable for me to use an invisible element (spaces or tabs) as a structural construction of a program (defining blocks), in a way much similar to Fortran, which I always considered weird (coming from the C world). This and the lack of the omnipresent, C-syntax end-of-line semicolon, prove to be a major boosting element when programming in Python. I must say that whatever lack in computer performance is overcome by the speed the programmer experiences when writing the software. This applies to general software, such as the App server that I am preparing, which is being written in Python using the Google App Engine, and I have to say that it just runs smoothly, no need for recompilations, clear syntax and one-line complex data-processing pieces of code.</p>

<p>Regarding data analysis, it is a little more complicated than Matlab’s clear orientation towards numerical linear algebra (where everything is a Matrix). Good comparisons and reasons supporting my view are</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/pythonforscientists/python-vs-matlab">https://sites.google.com/site/pythonforscientists/python-vs-matlab</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.stat.washington.edu/~hoytak/blog/whypython.html">http://www.stat.washington.edu/~hoytak/blog/whypython.html</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://stevetjoa.com/305/">http://stevetjoa.com/305/</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Now, going to Machine Learning specifics, sklearn has everything you need for the majority of the work a machine learning practitioner will ever need.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Data preprocessors, including text vectorizers and TF IDF preprocessors</li>
  <li>SVM implementations</li>
  <li>Stochastic Gradient Descent algorithms for fast regression and classification</li>
  <li>Random Forest and other ensemble methods for robust regression and classification</li>
  <li>Clustering algorithms</li>
  <li>Data dimensionality reduction algorithms such as LLE, ISOMAP and spectral embeddings</li>
  <li>Results presentation, including mean squared error for regression and precision/recall tables for classification. It even computes the area under the ROC curve.</li>
</ul>

<p>This, added to the clean, standardized and well-designed interface, which always has a .fit method for every object which performs the task of learning from samples, and then either a .transform method if the learning is unsupervised (such as LLE, ISOMAP, ICA, PCA, or the preprocessors, etc) or .predict if the learning is supervised (SVM, SGD, ensemble…). If enables a pipelining mechanism that allows us to build the whole pipeline from data reading to results output.</p>

<p>One of the lead programmers of the project, <a href="peekaboo-vision.blogspot.com.es">Andreas Müller</a> has a very insightful blog.</p>

<p>I decided to be more active on Kaggle. For the moment I scored 13th on the Leaderboard of the Amazon employee access competition that recently opened.</p>

<p>Last but not least, just to comment that future work seems to be bent on using the GPU to perform all the linear algebra. Check out</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.cs.toronto.edu/~tijmen/gnumpy.html">Gnumpy</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://deeplearning.net/tutorial/DBN.html">Deep Belief Networks</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://documen.tician.de/pycuda/tutorial.html">PyCUDA</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Git Workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/my-git-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-10T01:00:55+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/my-git-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past I had used CVS as most of the people. Git is much powerful, in so many levels. For starters, you never,
NEVER lose files. You can <strong>always</strong> go back to a previous version, the soft ware, or the hard. But Git requires a little
more attention on the part of the user than other control version systems. This starts by fixing the basic concepts
clearly.</p>

<h3 id="concepts">Concepts</h3>

<p>The concepts, from basic qto more complex, and also sorted by the first time you are likely to come across them, is:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Tracked file</strong>: A file that is under version control. You specifically told Git to track it at some point of its life.</li>
  <li><strong>Woring directory</strong>: This is the classical concept, your working copy of the project, including the files you
modify, the ones that are tracked and others that you want to leave untracked (such as IDE files or personal notes).</li>
  <li><strong>Local repository</strong>: This is <em>the Git repository stored on your local computer</em>. It is <em>not</em> your local working
directory, but the files stored in the <code>.git</code> directory within your working copy.</li>
  <li><strong>remote</strong>: A remote is a remote Git server that stores our project. Several remotes can exist for a project and we
always need to specify the remote to which we are going to send our changes.</li>
  <li><strong>Remote repository</strong>: The remote repository that stores the version of the project that everybody can see.</li>
  <li><strong>Branch</strong>: This is the usual concept of branch. Branches of the project may evolve in an independent way from each
other. All commits are attached to a branch. Local branches may not exist in the remote repository and remote branches
may have not been updated in your local repository at some point. The default branch is called <em>master</em>.</li>
  <li><strong>Conflict</strong>: Incompatible changes from a source were incorporated to a dirty copy (meaning that you modify something
that had been already modified), or you have a commit that modifies something already modified in the source you are
applying. You will need to resolve this by hand.</li>
  <li><strong>stash</strong>: Shelve your local changes. In other words, pack your dirty working copy and leave a clean working directory
that matches the contents of your local repository. This is important if you want to do operations on files that you
have changed on your working copy, since Git will complain otherwise.</li>
  <li><strong>unstash</strong>: Get the changes from the stash into your local copy, making it dirty if it was not. If it was not dirty
or you got changes from another branch or from the remote repository, you are likely to have conflicts and will need
to resolve them.</li>
  <li><strong>pull</strong>: Update remote changes in your local repository (and your working copy so you can see them). If you have
a dirty working copy you will need to stash your local changes.</li>
  <li><strong>Dirty local copy</strong>: Tracked files in the working directory that have been changed.</li>
  <li><strong>commit</strong>: A change in a tracked file (dirty local copy) that gets added to the local repository. You commit to a
branch.</li>
  <li><strong>push</strong>: The commits (local changes that now form part of your local repository) get sent to the remote repository
so that everybody can finally access them. This updates the remote branch.</li>
  <li><strong>merge</strong>: This happens when two members have changed the same tracked files on a branch in the the remote
repository. The last user in pushing the changes (<em>B</em>) will need to pull the changes that the first one (<em>A</em>) already pushed,
so that the official history was written firstly by <em>A</em>. The conflicts will most likely need to be resolved by
hand by <em>B</em>, since Git does not understand any particular language (and is not intelligent to decide on the conflicts
or have criteria to do so). Once merged, <em>B</em> ends up with a dirty working copy, that he needs to commit and then push.
This last push will be accepted by the remote repository server (if no one has put new stuff in the meantime).</li>
  <li><strong>rebase</strong>: This is a especially useful type of merge in which a user has not pulled down changes for a while and there
are a number of commits in the remote repository. If the user commits, then he can rebase the remote branch onto his,
so that his commit is merged on top of the remote commits. The user can then push to the remote branch and see his
changes reflected there. The rebase command is very versatile since it allows us to modify previous commits in our
repository.</li>
  <li><strong>reset</strong>: Set your branch to any commit in your repository. At this point a <strong>VERY IMPORTANT NOTE</strong> must be mentioned:
any repository, including the local one, stores commits. This means that commits <em>ALWAYS</em> survive, they are always
present, and one can always reset a branch head to a particular commit if the commit hash is available. It does not
matter that the commit had been “lost” in the branch chain.</li>
  <li><strong>cherry-pick</strong>: One can also cherry-pick a commit in the repository, given its hash, from any branch and apply it
to any other branch. Again, it does not matter that the picked commit does not currently appear on any branch, it
suffices for it to have been stored in the repository at some point.</li>
  <li><strong>log</strong>: This command is useful since it shows the chain of commits we have on our <em>local</em> repository that end up
in our current state. This does not show all the commits that once belonged to a branch if the branch was reset and
then new commits arrived (in a similar way to when we undo something in MS Word and then write new stuff, we cannot
redo). Useful for rebasing stuff.</li>
  <li><strong>reflog</strong>: This is <strong>ALL</strong> the repository history, including committed stuff, branch changes, pulled changes, etc.
You can find <strong>EVERYTHING</strong> here, even commits that were apparently “lost” from a branch. If you feel you have lost
a commit, just issue <code>git reflog</code> and cherry-pick from there.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="my-workflow">My workflow</h3>

<p>When you are developing a new feature for your project, want you want to do is branch the master branch (or any other,
but it makes sense to pick up the official state of the project and start from there).</p>

<p><code>bash 
git checkout -b newfeature
</code></p>

<p>This creates a <strong>local branch</strong>. We are interested in storing our changes remotely so that if something happens to our
local copy (major Git messup that is easy to just ignore and pull the remote, hard drive issues, computer issues,
get your stuff done in some other computer, etc), we have our changes in the remote server too.</p>

<p><code>bash
git push origin newfeature
git branch --set-origin=origin/newfeature
</code></p>

<p>This creates the <strong>remote branch</strong> and sets the default link to our local branch, so that we can push to it.</p>

<p>After this, we can do our changes. I normally spend some time with a feature and by the time I want to commit to master (when the changes are not enough
to be peer reviewed in a pull request to the master branch), some other workmate has committed something, which forces
me to <strong>pull</strong> and <strong>rebase</strong>.</p>

<p>Imagine that I am working on newfeature and I notice that master has changed. It is better to incorporate the remote
changes sooner so that conflicts are minimal. I first <strong>stash</strong> my local changes, since I will need to change branch
to pull master (you can do it from newfeature branch, but I like it this way).</p>

<p><code>bash
git stash
git checkout master
git pull
</code></p>

<p>Now we have the remote latest changes. We switch to the newfeature branch</p>

<p><code>bash
git checkout newfeature
git rebase -i master
</code></p>

<p>This tells git to get (local, which was just updated) commits onto the current branch, newfeature. Now newfeature is
updated with the latest master state. We can keep on working. Get our latest changes, the ones we stashed.</p>

<p><code>bash
git stash apply
</code></p>

<p>This applies the top of the stash to the current clean local branch, and does not remove them from the stash. I am
normally interested in keeping these changes just in case. I can later remove them with <code>git stash drop</code>. I sometimes
use <code>git stash pop</code> which applies changes <em>and</em> removes them from the stash. If I need to refer to the stash to get
a change that I know was there but am not sure it is on the top, then I use <code>git stash show --name-only</code>, which
gives me the names of the changed files.</p>

<p>When I feel I can commit (because I am done or because I want to store remotely)</p>

<p><code>bash
git commit -m "Message"
git push origin newfeature
</code></p>

<p>Which saves my commits in the remote branch (remote repository).</p>

<p>I sometimes need to modify something that I committed, because I forgot to include it (and we want our master history
to be clean of mistakes and easy to follow), I prepare my local changes (tracked files) for commit fixup. First I use
the <code>git add</code> command to add these files to the subsequent commit. This commit will be done in a special manner:
using the <code>--fixup=</code> modifier, which accepts the hash of the commit to be modified. This is an extremely versatile
modifier, since it allows us to modify commits buried deep beneath our current head. This creates a new commit chain
with the fixed commit and all the commits that followed it, with new versions adapted to the changes we have introduced
(and of course, all with new hashes, since they are all new commits).</p>

<p>I came across a very easy command pipe to do this, since adding files one by one is a time waster:</p>

<p><code>bash
git status | grep modified | cut -d: -f2 | xargs git add
</code></p>

<p>The command <code>status</code> gives us the modified files, among other stuff (untracked files, etc). I filter the modified files
(getting only the file name) and then add them as an argument to <code>git add</code>.</p>

<p>We now fix the particular commit. In this case, I get the commit hash with <code>git log</code>.</p>

<p><code>bash
git commit --fixup=24ee1df941679953529aabc3d0eef5727a44c094
</code></p>

<p>This creates a <em>new</em> commit on top of the rest. We need to squash everything so that git creates the new commit chain,
wich entirely different commits and with the fixing and fixed commits merged into one. If the commit is buried below
the head, you would use the commit previous to the one being fixed. Imagine this chain</p>

<p><code>bash
c0cf52f4a914641efdc635bbc6195b6bef084cdc Categories and other plugin stuff
021086446698443ee57858872e14e7ee8ca9e2e5 Remove deploy stuff that got added by mistake
24ee1df941679953529aabc3d0eef5727a44c094 First commit to my-source
7f49807d5c5651baccb6d66c504549713a7ae7d7 Site updated at 2015-01-05 15:12:45 UTC
</code></p>

<p>When you create the fixup commit, it will appear on top of the chain</p>

<p><code>bash
f36806a856994c8365e199a72501a5461ca99497 fixup! First commit to my-source
c0cf52f4a914641efdc635bbc6195b6bef084cdc Categories and other plugin stuff
021086446698443ee57858872e14e7ee8ca9e2e5 Remove deploy stuff that got added by mistake
24ee1df941679953529aabc3d0eef5727a44c094 First commit to my-source
7f49807d5c5651baccb6d66c504549713a7ae7d7 Site updated at 2015-01-05 15:12:45 UTC
</code></p>

<p>Then you autosquash the chain, selecting the commit previous to the fix</p>

<p><code>bash
git rebase -i --autosquash 7f49807d5c5651baccb6d66c504549713a7ae7d7
</code></p>

<p>The result is a new chain</p>

<p><code>bash
c927d675189eedd89d972663e2ef0ffe1438f4f7 Categories and other plugin stuff
e08ef8e27b3fd3c15e07a5e032e66a67a533ca3d Remove deploy stuff that got added by mistake
7d94aace9629272848382abfc217282c676f108e First commit to my-source
7f49807d5c5651baccb6d66c504549713a7ae7d7 Site updated at 2015-01-05 15:12:45 UTC
</code></p>

<p>Where the new <code>7d94aace9629272848382abfc217282c676f108e</code> contains the modifications needed.</p>

<p>In case the commit we want to fix is on top of the chain, the autosquash is simpler:</p>

<p><code>bash
git rebase -i --autosquash HEAD~2
</code></p>

<p>If I had pushed my branch to the remote repository, then I would have to force push, since there is no way my local
branch and the remote one are compatible. To do that, you need to be pretty sure nobody is in the process of
committing anything to that particular branch (this is not a problem if you are working on this feature on your own),
and issue</p>

<p><code>bash
git push origin newfeature -f
</code></p>

<p>Where origin is my remote repository name and <code>-f</code> overwrites the remote contents.</p>

<h3 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h3>

<p>We can see that we can modify our commit chain (resetting our branch head or fixing commits). Some people say it changes
the history, but I don’t see it that way). The true history is in the <strong>reflog</strong>.</p>

<p>Also, people might find it difficult to think of the usefulness of having several remote repositories. For example, this
blog has a remote which is, obviously, Github pages, and it is where the stuff under <code>_deploy</code> gets sebt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IPython Notebook for Data Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/12/14/ipython-notebook-for-data-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-14T11:47:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/12/14/ipython-notebook-for-data-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A nice tool for both exploratory analysis and teaching is IPython Notebook. It consists of a web server executing
Python commands on an IPython interpreter and a set of Javascript files and CSS style sheets to layout the input and
output correctly and nicely. By connecting to the URL where the server is listening, you access to a book of pages,
each of one contains data input lines in Python and their corresponding beautified output, which can include images
and charts generated by <em>Matplotlib</em> or any other library that produces graphical output.</p>

<p>In the following, I wanted to face a recurrent problem that I have been facing in the past, derived from using
general tools such as Matlab for data analysis tasks. The problem with general tools is that they are easy to grasp and
feel confident with them, maybe too confident. In the case of Matlab, I became too comfortable with the flexibility of
matrices, which allow you to get started quickly since you can easily move data blocks around, but then force you to 
implement your in-house algorithms for data munging, or at least turn you too lazy to look for them 
(in the spirit of “that’ll only take me half an hour and then I’ll devote my time to productive
coding”).</p>

<p>I felt picky today, so I opened up my IPython Notebook server. For data munging, as everything else, one must not
re-invent the wheel, but let oneself use one of the excellent libraries out there. Pandas is an excellent example of
data munging libraries. Here we are going to align two time series, and the problem is the same than in the previous
post, i.e., align two time series with different time indices, such as two stock prices belonging to different markets,
observing different holidays (see the full description and solution in my previous post).</p>

<p>To do that, we concluded that the alignment could be made by merging two Pandas’ DataFrame objects, each containing
a series data (which can be multidimensional, and whose cells will be mixed), which produces some <em>NA</em>s. Then we could
apply the <em>gap</em> <em>NA</em> filling policy, which took the last valid value on each series.</p>

<p>The result, prettified by IPy Notebook can be seen in the figure to the right (you can click on it, a pop up will show
thanks to the <a href="https://github.com/rayfaddis/octopress-BootstrapModal">Bootstrap Image Pop plugin</a>, of which I will
talk in the following post).</p>

<p><!-- Image -->
<a id="img-7" class="imgModal floatRight" href="#imgModal-7" data-toggle="modal">
  <img src="/images/ipython-notebook.png" width="342" height="193" title="Click for larger view." />
</a>
<div style="float: none;"></div>

<!-- Modal -->
<div class="modal fade" id="imgModal-7" tabindex="-1" role="dialog" aria-labelledby="imgModal-7Label" aria-hidden="true">
  <div class="modal-dialog">
    <div class="modal-content">
      <div class="modal-header">
        <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal" aria-hidden="true">&times;</button>
      </div>
      <div class="modal-body">
        <img src="/images/ipython-notebook.png" width="1366" height="771" />
      </div>
      <div class="modal-footer">
        <button type="button" class="btn btn-primary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
      </div>
    </div><!-- /.modal-content -->
  </div><!-- /.modal-dialog -->
</div><!-- /.modal --></p>

<p>As you can see, this makes it especially adequate for information propagation environments such as board presentations
of data analytics or classroom interactive teaching. In the latter case, it is easy to imaging students connecting to
the teacher’s server and inputting their commands, while the teacher corrects them when they are wrong. To update items
in real time, IPy Notebook should contemplate using websockets or any kind of server side events, which I believe
does not so far.</p>

<p>Anyway, it is a great tool to present results in a very neat way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Future of Data Analysis Tools: Python, Web Technologies]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/27/the-future-of-data-analysis-tools/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-27T12:01:19+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/27/the-future-of-data-analysis-tools</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past years I have observed a shift, or convergence one might say, in the tools used in several disciplines
involving data handling or processing. An easy example is this blog, which is made with 
<a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, a tool heavily based on <em>nerdy</em> concepts such as compilation, version control,
modular building and Markdown syntax, and tools such as Git and the Ruby toolkit. This makes blogging more similar
to software development, as I hinted <a href="/blog/2014/11/01/my-new-blog/">on my first post on this blog</a>.</p>

<p>We find this shift to be a real convergence in the case of data analysis and software development, specifically,
web software development and scripting with Python. This is almost self evident and has been noted previously, in fact,
a blog entry talking about
<a href="http://www.talyarkoni.org/blog/2013/11/18/the-homogenization-of-scientific-computing-or-why-python-is-steadily-eating-other-languages-lunch/">pythonification of a scientist’s data toolkit</a>
and thinking about my own data analysis toolkit got me writing about this.</p>

<h3 id="the-past">The past</h3>

<p>Previously, I relied primarily on Matlab. Matlab mostly considers matrices as the primary building block in programs
(cells are another very useful structure to consider when elements of a set do not share the same dimension or types).
Everything is a matrix, a hyper-rectangle of things, from scalars to multi-dimensional matrices. This makes moving data
in blocks very easy, since this constitutes an atomic vectorial operation. However, this reduction to the general
case exposes several problems that one normally faces during the data analysis process. For example, one might be
interested in correlating sells with the social sentiment about our product. This involves scraping candidate web
pages, storing interesting parts of the text, performing sentiment analysis, aggregating by date and aligning with
sells by date. This is an unbearable task to do by moving data blocks in Matlab.</p>

<p>R, as in <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">GNU R-Project</a> is a more complete framework for data munging, since it seeks to
replicate the S statistical language in its origins. R, which has the concept of objects, defines a dataframe class
that specifically considers column as attributes and rows as instances, defines a set of methods that allow us to
deal with specialized tasks like sorting, filtering or rearranging. Although I have used R in the past, I never came to
like it despite the hught support by the community. I feel that some piece is missing, and that is maybe the heavily
typing for a data analysis language, poor language-level support for functional paradigms which are great for data
munging (map, reduce, filter and the like). Algorithms must be implemented in an imperative setting, which isn’t
sometimes the best option.</p>

<h3 id="the-present">The present</h3>

<p>Python comes in the middle of it all. It supports functional paradigms such as lambda functions (functions defined
where they are used), functions as first-class objects, and classical operations on collections. On the other hand,
Python has increasingly getting more support from the community and the amount of available libraries is astonishing.
It is true that the support for statistical analysis in Python cannot be compared to that or R yet, but Python is
steadily catching up, with ever increasing scientists switching in all disciplines. A number of mature projects
exist in all the areas, ranging from general Statistics to Neuroimaging. Several bridges exist to R packages with no
native counterpart. This, the language support for advanced features, optimized packages such as
<a href="www.lfd.uci.edu/~gohlke/pythonlibs/">Cristoph Golke’s</a> (which include NumPy and SciPy versions statically compiled
against the highly efficient Intel’s MKL BLAS distributions) and the extra toolset derived from years of using
Python as a generalist scripting data (including a highly-productive web toolset), makes Python a worthy
next-generation substitute for R.</p>

<p>Imagine that we collect two time series of stock prices that originated in two different markets. These two markets
observe different holidays, so the raw time series that we get are unaligned (this is true for Yahoo Finance historical
data, for example). Our data pre-processing task is to align the data, keeping the last valid price for holidays where
the other market is open.</p>

<p>Pandas is a Python library that includes much of R functionality and is extremely handy for this kind of data munging
tasks. By creating DataFrame objects from our raw data, we access the kind of functionality we need. In this case, once
we have two DataFrame objects, <em>dt1</em> and <em>dt2</em>, where we simulates two weeks of data, by starting on Monday, 1st,
and ending on Friday, 12th. The first market observes a holiday on Friday the 5th, while the second observes a
holiday on Monday, 1st. We define the dataframes as follows:</p>

<p><code>python
dt1 = DataFrame({'date' : [1,2,3,4,8,9,10,11,12], 'value' : [100,101,102,103,104,105,106,107,108]})
dt2 = DataFrame({'date' : [1,2,3,4,5,9,10,11,12], 'value' : [100,101,102,103,104,105,106,107,108]})
</code></p>

<p>To successfully mix the data toether, we can use the merge function on the column date, specifying the <em>outer</em> merging
method, which keeps data rows coming from both dataframes.</p>

<p><code>python
dt1.merge(dt2, on=['date'], how='outer')
</code></p>

<p>This will output</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th style="text-align: center">date</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">value_x</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">value_y</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">100</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">100</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">2</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">101</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">101</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">102</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">102</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">4</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">103</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">103</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">8</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">104</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">NaN</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">9</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">105</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">105</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">10</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">106</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">106</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">11</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">107</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">107</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">12</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">108</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">108</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">5</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">NaN</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">104</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>We notice the dates are unsorted due to using the first dataframe, which skips friday (date 8 would be unsorted if we
were to use the <em>dt2</em> object). We sort on the <em>date</em> column. However, there is a bigger problem, we see NaNs,
Not a number values for column of a dataframe not defined in the other, since this is the usual outcome from the
outer merge. In this case, the <em>fillna</em> method of the DataFrame class with the <em>gap</em> policy will fit our purposes
(carry over the last valid value).</p>

<p><code>python
dt1.merge(dt2, on=['date'], how='outer').sort(columns=['date']).fillna(method='pad')
</code></p>

<p>The result of all steps is</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th style="text-align: center">date</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">value_x</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">value_y</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">100</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">100</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">2</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">101</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">101</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">102</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">102</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">4</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">103</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">103</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">5</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">103</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">104</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">8</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">104</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">104</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">9</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">105</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">105</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">10</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">106</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">106</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">11</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">107</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">107</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">12</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">108</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">108</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Of course, we have excellent IDEs to work with, ranging from generalist tools and plugins for major IDE frameworks
such as Eclipse and IntelliJ IDEA, to more specialized editors such as the Matlab-like Spyder, IPython Notebook (embedded
in the IPython executable, which can be started with the option <code>-notebook</code>). Also, emerging editors such as the
celebrated Sublime Text and Light Table fully support Python.</p>

<h3 id="data-visualization-past-and-present">Data visualization: past and present</h3>

<p>An often overlooked side is data visualization. As people coming from the engineering side, where doing ugly and
hard to use things is almost a badge of pride, we never care about how our results look as long as they are correct
(in a sense that they fulfill their functional requirements). Presentation is not only important from the aesthetic
point of view, but can also help the experts discover patterns in the data that offer previously unknown clues about
the nature of our data.</p>

<p>Plotting Matlab graphs and pasting them on a Word document was the normal. R has an impressive set of graphical tools
that cope with the most exigent user. For the presentations, using PowerPoint was the thing to do in corporate
environments and the most adventurous could embark on the quest of using Latex Beamer for this purpose. Not any more.</p>

<p>The new normal will be web technologies. Web browsers are the most advanced graphical tool available to any user in the
world. The dynamic capabilities achieved by both CSS and Javascript make any other technology pale. To easy the burden
of dealing with raw CSS and Javascript, a number of libraries have been built on top of the browser native support.
Some of these rise above the others. I must mention <a href="http://d3js.org">D3js</a>, an impressive graphical library with
anything a data scientist with graphical needs might need. Visit their examples page to get a glance of the
capabilities.</p>

<iframe width="720" height="480" marginheight="-500" marginwidth="-300" src="http://mbostock.github.io/d3/talk/20111018/collision.html"></iframe>

<p>Lastly, PowerPoint and Latex Beamer users with professional needs will both shift to browser presentation technologies
such as <a href="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/">RevealJS</a>, which can be complemented with Latex renderers to achieve perfect
results for the mathematical formulae, on top of superior interactions.</p>

<iframe width="720" height="480" src="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/"></iframe>

<h3 id="the-future">The future</h3>

<p>A large shift towards Python can be expected, especially in rapid prototyping. Even though R is not going away soon,
Python bindings will relegate R to a second class language, so to speak, in the same way as Fortran is today, this is,
there are many classical algorithms written in Fortran in the 70’s and 80’s still being in production today. This
includes a huge number of well-known and widely-used linear algebra libraries such as Netlib’s BLAS and LAPACK, which
are currently interfaced to other languages such as R.</p>

<p>Also, functional programming should play a role in data analysis. Lisps variants have an important advantage over imperative
paradigms such as working naturally with monads. This makes the use of the monad <em>some</em> very useful for list processing.
For example, in closure we can write</p>

<p>&#8220;` clojure
(def data [1 2 3 4])</p>

<p>(some-&gt; data
        process1
        process2
        process3)
&#8220;`</p>

<p>which prevents us from using a large chain of nested if blocks for this conditional processing. However, Lisp syntax
is not well suited for rapid prototyping, where data scientists prefer a more imperative approach to define global
variables for later processing</p>

<p><code>python
X = np.array([1,2,3,4])
</code></p>

<p>Functional languages might become, if not a rapid prototyping choice, indeed a data system deployment choice, since
a lot more data processing and state handling will need to be done. It is worth mentioning
<a href="http://clojure.github.io/clojure/clojure.zip-api.html">zippers</a>,
<a href="https://clojure.github.io/clojure/clojure.walk-api.html">walkers</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/clojure/core.match">match</a>, three libraries that make the programmer’s life easier by orders of
magnitude when dealing with data processing, but I will devote an article to them.</p>

<p>Regarding data visualization, it will be done primarily with web technologies on the browser, with AJAX data requests
to the server were the data processing and storage are done. Here, technologies such as D3js will be a must.</p>

<h3 id="summary">Summary</h3>

<p>In the future, it is conceivable to use an integrated framework that analyzes data with Python libraries and then
presents the results via a Python web server to multiple browsers.</p>

<p>As well as Java will not totally go away in the enterprise software development world, neither will current data processing
technologies such as Excel, PowerPoint, Matlab or R, since they have die hard niches. In particular, the huge amount of
existing libraries will need time to be adapted to Python.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My New Blog in Github Pages + Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/my-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T23:19:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/my-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, welcome to my shiny new blog. It is long since I have been wanting to set up a professional blog, something that
others call a <em>blog for hackers</em>. It is called like that, I believe, because no online, fancy wysiwyg editor is used and
instead you use professional tools such as Git and a bunch of well crafted Ruby scripts, although you only need to 
follow a cookbook (from which a small deviation may break everything down and you need to hack around a little bit,
for real).</p>

<p>Well, I want to test its features now. I am editing with IntelliJ and Markdown. Nothing spectacular, it might be my
personal set up, because the plugin at my job is definitely more functional.</p>

<p>Now a code snippet. I follow the instructions at Octopress’ website.</p>

<p><code>bash
env x='() { :;}; echo vulnerable' bash -c "echo this is a test"
</code></p>

<p>Check. Beautiful. Lovin’ it.</p>

<p>Now for my second prerequisite which was a big concern for me regarding moving to a blogging platform: maths! I wan’t
to be able to edit in Latex. The lack of it is a no go. Luckily, I found
<a href="http://www.idryman.org/blog/2012/03/10/writing-math-equations-on-octopress/">this helpful blog post</a>, which describes how
to do precisely that. Testing:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\int_a^b f(x) dx = F(b) - F(a)
</script>

<p>Check. Awesome! Sold!</p>

<p>Apparently, you write your post in this markdown file, which you compile with the provided tool, which gets sucked up
by a local web server that helps you visualize your results, before pushing it up to your Github repo. I like that.</p>

<p>Let be it! I am moving to Github Pages + Octopress.</p>

<p>Edit: I forgot to test Youtube video insertion. <del>Apparently you need a <a href="https://github.com/optikfluffel/octopress-responsive-video-embed">plugin</a></del> 
This is done by pasting the <em>iframe</em> tag as given by youtube.
OK, cloned, copied Ruby files and test (with current time position including <em>?start=253</em>):</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/X6s6YKlTpfw?start=253" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>No responsiveness as of yet, but it’s fine for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
