<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Computation | The Analytic Bastard]]></title>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/categories/computation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-09T15:19:53+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Analytic Bastard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google's Original Page Rank Implementation]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/02/08/google-original-page-rank/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-08T11:31:03+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/02/08/google-original-page-rank</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever since I took a good course on Matrix Analysis, I have been curious about how Google’s Page Rank algorithm was
related to Matrix theory, because I never got a chance to have a look at it when I studied computer systems.</p>

<p>Imagine the graph of web pages visited by Google crawlers, where <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{M}</script> is the adjacency matrix with the outgoing
links in the columns, where each edge in the web page <script type="math/tex">i</script> pointing to a web page <script type="math/tex">j</script> (which can be the same)
has a score of <script type="math/tex">\frac{1}{n_i}</script>, where <script type="math/tex">n_i</script> is the number of outgoing links in the webpage <script type="math/tex">i</script>. This matrix might
present a number of problems with actual graphs, so what Google did was to include page self references and random
jumps between pages with a small probability given by a parameter <script type="math/tex">\beta</script>.</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\mathbf{G} = \beta \mathbf{M} + (1-\beta) \frac{\mathbf{1} \mathbf{1}^T}{N}</script>

<p>where <script type="math/tex">N</script> is the total number of web pages in the system and <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{1}</script> is the vector of all ones of size <script type="math/tex">N</script>.</p>

<p><script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}</script>, being a stochastic matrix, has one as the largest eigenvalue (in module). This can be proved by taking
<script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}^T \mathbf{1}=\mathbf{1}</script>, and since <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}^T = (\mathbf{P}^{-1})^{-T} \mathbf{D} \mathbf{P}{-T}</script>,
where <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{P}</script> diagonalizes <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}</script> and <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{D}</script> is the resulting diagonal matrix with the eigenvalues
of both <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}</script> and <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G^{T}}</script>. Thus one is also the largest eigenvalue of <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}</script>. Proving that
this is in fact the largest can be done by applyting the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gershgorin_circle_theorem">Gershgoring circle theorem</a>.</p>

<p>Intuitively, applyting <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}</script> several times has the effect of building a power matrix <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}^M</script> whose
largest eigenvalue is also one, but the rest are the power of elements less than one, meaning that each power decreases
all the eigenvalues except the first one. This has the effect of minimizing the component of any vector (the projection)
in the subspace spanned by the eigenvector corresponding to any eigenvalue except the first one. Eventually, all of them
reach zero, leaving only the component of the original vector in the subspace of the eigenvector corresponding to the
largest eigenvalue. This means
<script type="math/tex">\mathbf{G}^M \mathbf{x} \rightarrow \mathbf{w}</script>, as <script type="math/tex">M</script> tends to infinite, where <script type="math/tex">\mathbf{w}</script> is the dominan
eigenvector (the one corresponding to the eigenvalue one).</p>

<p>The elements of this vectors are the important for all the pages registered on the database by the crawlers or
robots.</p>

<p>Obviously this demands a lot of computation since the web is ever changing and this power method would need to be
performed in batch intermitently, so efficient implementations are needed (based on Map Reduce or not).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
