<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hacking | The Analytic Bastard]]></title>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/categories/hacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-22T23:53:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Analytic Bastard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hackintosh]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/01/06/hackintosh/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-06T01:24:36+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2015/01/06/hackintosh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got an ASUS K55VD laptop nearly two years ago and the motherboard broke down without possibility of repair. Not being
able to repair it (I had several technical service shops working on it) was a sting on my heart. Then I recently spotted
an ASUS K55A motherboard (essentially the same except the NVidia 610M chip and no 2 GB external video RAM soldered into
the motherboard) on eBay. That was good enough for me, and I got the item for a very good price.</p>

<p>I managed to assemble the thing and I was lucky enough to get it working. So I ended up with two similar configurations.
I have a decent Ubuntu virtual machine on my Windows laptop, and I use it to play some games from time to time, so I
wanted this spare laptop to be useful in some other meaningful sense. It occurred to me that I could install Mac OSX
and have access to Apple’s tools to compile iOS apps for the iPhone.</p>

<p>Well, you must know that surfing the world of Hackintosh is overwhelming. The hacking is so volatile and the dependency
on each piece of hardware so extreme, that it becomes a pain in the ass for anybody. I don’t know whether to praise or
take pity of the Hackintosh scene such as Tonymacx86, RehabMan, Niresh, etc.</p>

<p>Well, I had a Mac virtual machine on my other laptop, so I downloaded Yosemite and created an installation USB. First
problem, my USB is not bootable. I don’t know whether this problem came from creating it from the virtual machine
(which needs to access the hardware in a non-native way through the host OS), but this was solved by using my Ubuntu
installation to create a HFS+ bootable partition with gParted (subsequent retries with Apple’s disk utility crashed my OSX VM).
With a bootable USB HFS+ partition, I could create a Yosemite installation USB with <a href="http://www.tonymacx86.com/445-unibeast-install-os-x-yosemite-any-supported-intel-based-pc.html">Unibeast</a>.
I must add that I got the Niresh distribution of Mountain Lion and Mavericks, but could not make it work either
(I don’t remember what the problem was).</p>

<p>Now, booting into the setup, I had some problems with my laptop keyboard and mouse not being recognized, so there was no
possibility of installing the software. What I did was installing <a href="http://www.tonymacx86.com/multibeast/">Multibeast</a>
<strong>on the USB drive</strong>, adding PS/2 Mouse and Keyboard support in the Multibeast menu (again from the 
virtual machine, to the created USB). With a workable-enough USB installation drive, I removed my previous Windows
partition and installed the vanilla Mac OSX. Then I added the same multibeast support. After booting, my motherboard
would not show my OSX installation as a boot option. I could only boot with my USB and choosing the installation as
partition to start from. I decided to use the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/cloverefiboot/">Clover</a> bootloader,
which allowed my motherboard to show an EFI startup partition. After some more tweaking, this allowed me to boot from
my Mac OS X installation. Full resolution, no sound. To get sound, I installed VoodooHDA, which created audio feedback.
To solve this, the iGain setting from the VoodooHDA config panel must be set to low or zero. The configuration does not
persist, so one might choose to edit the kext <code>Config.plist</code> and set it there (and rebuild the caches!!!) or use
the VoodooHDA panel config (I don’t quite remember the details of this so you better google it).</p>

<p>I noticed a blinking effect when the computer showed the login screen, and investigating it further revealed that I had
no graphics acceleration. Injecting the 0x01660003 code in Clover had no effect, nor did using any other boot flag. At
this point I was desperate. I decided to run Multibeast once again against my OS X installation and install pretty much
any appealing driver. This (albeit some minor problems with the PS/2 drivers causing a halt in the boot process, solved
my manually deleting the drivers -and updating the cache!!!) granted me full graphics acceleration.</p>

<p><!-- Image -->
<a id="img-10" class="imgModal floatRight" href="#imgModal-10" data-toggle="modal">
  <img src="/images/yosemite.png" width="342" height="192" title="Click for larger view." />
</a>
<div style="float: none;"></div>

<!-- Modal -->
<div class="modal fade" id="imgModal-10" tabindex="-1" role="dialog" aria-labelledby="imgModal-10Label" aria-hidden="true">
  <div class="modal-dialog">
    <div class="modal-content">
      <div class="modal-header">
        <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal" aria-hidden="true">&times;</button>
      </div>
      <div class="modal-body">
        <img src="/images/yosemite.png" width="1366" height="768" />
      </div>
      <div class="modal-footer">
        <button type="button" class="btn btn-primary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
      </div>
    </div><!-- /.modal-content -->
  </div><!-- /.modal-dialog -->
</div><!-- /.modal --></p>

<p>The Wifi card of this laptop (AR5B925) is not compatible since Apple has not released kexts for this chip, nor has any
hacker done so. I got hold of an AR5B97 which is compatible, and installing the <a href="http://www.tonymacx86.com/network/104850-guide-airport-pcie-half-mini-v2.html">toledaARPT.kext</a>
with the Kext Helper. It is wonderful now to have Internet conectivity, though the Bluetooth is nowhere to be seen,
despite this card having it.</p>

<p>This is it, a process that spanned several days summarized in a small post. I hope it provides you with clues if your
issues are simmilar, but then again, everybody gets different symptoms when dealing with his own Hackintosh.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
