<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Computing | The Analytic Bastard]]></title>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/categories/computing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-21T00:31:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Analytic Bastard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My New Blog in Github Pages + Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/my-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T23:19:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/my-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, welcome to my shiny new blog. It is long since I have been wanting to set up a professional blog, something that
others call a <em>blog for hackers</em>. It is called like that, I believe, because no online, fancy wysiwyg editor is used and
instead you use professional tools such as Git and a bunch of well crafted Ruby scripts, although you only need to 
follow a cookbook (from which a small deviation may break everything down and you need to hack around a little bit,
for real).</p>

<p>Well, I want to test its features now. I am editing with IntelliJ and Markdown. Nothing spectacular, it might be my
personal set up, because the plugin at my job is definitely more functional.</p>

<p>Now a code snippet. I follow the instructions at Octopress’ website.</p>

<p><code>bash
env x='() { :;}; echo vulnerable' bash -c "echo this is a test"
</code></p>

<p>Check. Beautiful. Lovin’ it.</p>

<p>Now for my second prerequisite which was a big concern for me regarding moving to a blogging platform: maths! I wan’t
to be able to edit in Latex. The lack of it is a no go. Luckily, I found
<a href="http://www.idryman.org/blog/2012/03/10/writing-math-equations-on-octopress/">this helpful blog post</a>, which describes how
to do precisely that. Testing:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\int_a^b f(x) dx = F(b) - F(a)
</script>

<p>Check. Awesome! Sold!</p>

<p>Apparently, you write your post in this markdown file, which you compile with the provided tool, which gets sucked up
by a local web server that helps you visualize your results, before pushing it up to your Github repo. I like that.</p>

<p>Let be it! I am moving to Github Pages + Octopress.</p>

<p>Edit: I forgot to test Youtube video insertion. <del>Apparently you need a <a href="https://github.com/optikfluffel/octopress-responsive-video-embed">plugin</a></del> 
This is done by pasting the <em>iframe</em> tag as given by youtube.
OK, cloned, copied Ruby files and test (with current time position including <em>?start=253</em>):</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/X6s6YKlTpfw?start=253" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>No responsiveness as of yet, but it’s fine for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
