<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mathematics - Geometry | The Analytic Bastard]]></title>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/categories/mathematics-geometry/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-09T15:31:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Analytic Bastard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pythagorean Theorem]]></title>
    <link href="http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/06/pythagorean-theorem/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-06T17:24:02+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://analyticbastard.github.io/blog/2014/11/06/pythagorean-theorem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Pythagorean Theorem is almost mainstream, everybody knows what it is about, yet not so many people know how to prove
it. Here is a proof that I consider to be the easiest one. It’s very analytic and avoids any geometric complications
 such as triangle similarity considerations.</p>

<p>Now, for this proof, you need to know basic geometrical notions such as the area of a square and the area of right
triangles.</p>

<p>Let a (large) square, be cut by a reflecting straight line such as the line builds an inner square and four right 
triangles, such as in the figure below. </p>

<p>Let one of the segments cut by the reflecting line be called $a$, and let the other be called $b$, which makes the
side of the large outer triangle $(a+b)$. In the smaller square,
let the side of the inner square be called $c$. These are the legs and the hypotenuse of the four right triangles.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/pythagorean.png" width="400" height="400" title="‘Pythagorean theorem’ ‘images’" ></p>

<p>Now, we know that the area $L$ of the large is its side squared, if arithmetic holds, 
<script type="math/tex">
L=(a+b)^2=a^2 + b^2 + 2ab
</script> </p>

<p>On the other hand, the large outer square is made up of four right triangles, whose individual area is $\frac{ab}{2}$ and
the inner square, whose area is $c^2$. Thus</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
L=4 \times \frac{ab}{2} + c^2
</script>

<p>Equating both expressions, we can arrive at the result of the theorem</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
a^2 + b^2 + 2ab = 4 \frac{ab}{2} + c^2 \\
a^2 + b^2 + 2ab = 2 \times ab + c^2\\
a^2 + b^2 = c^2
</script>

<p>Notice that only axioms about angle reflection and straight lines are needed for this theorem (for example, we need
to establish that a straight line reflects on another straight line with the complementary angle of both straight lines).</p>

<p>I made the image above and it is copylefted. If you want to use the SVG version, feel free to drop me an email.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
